<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>blog.mmolina.me</title>
<link>https://blog.mmolina.me/</link>
<atom:link href="https://blog.mmolina.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2025-06 Book dump</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-06-Book-dump.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="i-have-no-mouth-and-i-must-scream-harlan-ellison" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="i-have-no-mouth-and-i-must-scream-harlan-ellison">I Have No Mouth And I Must Scream Harlan-Ellison</h2>
<p>I liked the short book. More than the book itself, I was drawn to the concept it explored—the aftermath of AGI whose goals are twisted and misaligned with humanity.</p>
<p>That said, I couldn’t fully inhabit the characters. Perhaps the brevity of the story limited this, or perhaps the narrative served the concept rather than the other way around. Either way, it was a letdown for me as a reader—I like to be immersed in the story. It felt too much like an episode of Friday Forbidden Tales from Bae Jin Soo <sup>1</sup></p>
<p>That persistent sense of “I’m here for the concept, not the story” stayed with me throughout. Maybe I came in with inflated expectations, having heard good things about it. So the disappointment may stem less from the author’s execution than from my own assumptions.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Not a critique of the webtoon—I love it, and the format suits a focus on concepts with throwaway characters. That said, I think Bae Jin Soo does a good job avoiding narrative dissonance.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>review</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-06-Book-dump.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Series and Movies that break expectations — but in a bad way</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-06-Series-and-Movies-that-break-expectations-but-in-a-bad-way.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I want to talk about what makes a piece of culture <em>bad</em>. Alice-in-the-Borderland, for example: bad, yet disguised within a concept I’m a sucker for.</p>
<p>I believe it’s the same phenomenon I observed while watching Attack-on-Titan, The-Platform, and The-Cube. Really captivating premises, but much feels <em>off</em>. It’s as if the way characters behave almost never aligns with what the viewer expects — and we slowly get used to it. Eventually, this strangeness is incorporated into our expectations. Not only is this off-putting, but subsequent moments further exacerbate the problem.</p>
<p>The uniqueness of the concepts taps into a mysterious part of my brain that compels me to keep watching. And then I <em>continue</em> watching only to satisfy the desire to see the concept explored to its end — to see what the authors and directors came up with. But this doesn’t make a show good. It’s <em>primal</em>, too primal; the substance isn’t there.</p>
<p>By “substance,” I mean a coherent story. One that tells itself — without relying on (what I consider) lazy narrative devices like flashbacks and long monologues. A good story isn’t afraid to surprise us — by breaking expectations. We anticipate something, but it <em>doesn’t</em> happen. That’s the surprise.</p>
<p>What happens next is what’s decisive.</p>
<p>Game-of-Thrones, especially the early seasons, excels here. You witness character development, and soon you get used to having your expectations broken again and again. But you’re not confused when Lord Frey acts as he does during the Red Wedding. From a humane perspective, it’s shocking; but from a narrative one, it makes perfect sense. The story caught us off guard, but it added up. We could interpolate Lord Frey’s behavior and justify it internally.</p>
<p>Contrast that with Alice in Borderland — a prime example of a strong concept executed poorly. Think Squid Game but on a larger scale and with anime aesthetics. Players must compete in games to earn “life visas” to survive. And maybe I’m being unfair — perhaps “they’re just acting like they did in the manga.” But an adaptation faces a choice: blandly port the original, or make it shine in its new form. They chose the former.</p>
<p>There’s a disturbing lack of questions when there should be more. A lack of reaction when there should be some. Cultural differences? Maybe. But the more I think about it, the less satisfying it feels to blame the acting. I wanted the <em>concept</em> to work — not just as an idea, but in the realm of narrative expectations. I wanted the <em>story</em> to be good.</p>
<p>To be fair, I loved some aspects. I like how anime often provides structure to abstract ideas. This show uses a clever system: each game has a playing card that indicates both difficulty and type. A 4 of Hearts is a difficulty-4 emotional game. It’s intuitive, shareable, and opens space for fan speculation and invention. A clear win.</p>
<p>And the Beach — a hedonist cult mandating swimsuits — was brilliant. Conceptually, it’s chef’s kiss. But lore-wise and acting-wise? Disaster. Every game ends in the last possible second. Throwaway characters blurt dumb, expository lines: “No… it can’t be… They are manipulating us—” Of course they are, dumbfuck! You’re in some alternate dimension playing lethal games, and <em>now</em> you realize this? And you shout it in front of everyone?</p>
<p>And the protagonist — the most textbook depiction of a nerdy gamer. Alienated father, golden-boy brother, self-doubt. So predictable it hurts.</p>
<p>Then they decide to chase after suspicious cars — not sneakily, just outright sprinting down an empty street. The best part? It kind of works…? Until they get caught five minutes later near the enemy base, after a dramatic little chat. That might’ve been the most believable moment in the whole thing.</p>
<p>Seriously, what?</p>
<p>This Narrative-Dissonance — between promising premise and broken execution — highlights a recurring flaw in certain speculative fiction: the idea alone is compelling, but the narrative architecture collapses under scrutiny. Good stories must do more than dangle a mystery or provoke a primal hook; they must earn trust through consistent internal logic and character integrity. No amount of clever framing or aesthetic flourish can substitute for the absence of story.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-06-Series-and-Movies-that-break-expectations-but-in-a-bad-way.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hyperfocus of the week - Refraction, Evolution and Belugas</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Hyperfocus-of-the-week-Refraction-Evolution-and-Belugas.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I became suddenly interested in how Beluga whales gained their Melon — this bulbous, gelatinous part on the top of their head. It’s so weird, I had no idea about its function!</p>
<p>Turns it out it’s used for communication and Echolocation. It contains fats of different densities which uses a phenomena known as Refraction to bend the wave and focalize into a beam. Refraction happens when a sound wave passes between two mediums that affect the speed of the wave differently.</p>
<p>Let’s take sound waves passing from the air to the water: the speed increases in the water, since water is denser and thus molecules of water can bounce into each other more easily than the ones in the air — in the air they are space out.</p>
<p>But swap the sound wave to a light wave and the behavior is the opposite: light travels <em>slowers</em> in water. This happens because water scatters the rays as they travel, opposed to the usually straight path they do in vacuum or air — although in air there’s still scattering but less pronounced.</p>
<p>A small trivia about this last fact: this gives rise to orange-y, red-y sunsets, since light of different wavelengths are scattered with varying levels: red-sh waves are longer and are more resistant to scattering, blu-sh ones are shorter and thus bump more easily into dust, water vapor or things that can scatter them.</p>
<p>Coming back to refraction, if the difference between mediums is big enough and the waves comes in steep in relation to the normal of the interface between them, Total Reflexion can happen. Instead of the wave entering the new medium with a change in its angle it bounces back to the same medium — like a rubber ball thrown onto the ground at an angle.</p>
<p>Cool. We covered the first part of my obsession of the last three days. The second part is how this gelatinous thing <em>evolved</em> in the first place. Beyond just the Beluga’s melon, I was interested in how these highly-specialized organs evolve in the first place: it must had no purpose when it first started appearing due to a random mutation.</p>
<p>One possibility is that a limited proto-version of the organ showed up and the trait got passed forward since it didn’t <em>harm</em> the individual’s fitness. It was just there — and suddenly because of environmental changes it got used for the first time. Now the selection happens in the standard way we are used to: the fittest ‘melons’ got passed forward, since it provided critical advantages for survival. Therefore, it could have been once a Neutral-Mutation.</p>
<p>I just looked online for other possibilities and was baffled to find a <a href="http://www.christcreated.com/pro/biology/adaption/irreducible-complexity/dolphin-melon/">contra-evolution christian website citing dolphin’s melon as an example of a complex structure impossible to have evolved step-by-step.</a> It cites Sarfati, 1999:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For such an organ to have evolved, random mutations must have formed the right enzymes to make the lipids to be deposited in the right places and shape. &nbsp;A gradual step-by-step evolution of the organ is not feasible, because until the lipids were fully formed and at least partly in the right place and shape, they would have been of no use. &nbsp;Therefore, natural selection would not have favored incomplete intermediate forms.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At first it makes sense to refute evolution of features that doesn’t lead to a better survival of the individual <em>also</em> in the incremental evolutionary stages. However, it could have been there as a proto-version — not harming the fitness — and some individual had the bare minimum of mutations necessary for it use for echolocation, even if rudimentary. This would have lend the individual an advantage, making it better at passing the genes forward. Why couldn’t this be an explanation? It seems possible.</p>
<p>Or it could be an example of Exaptation: the melon could have served (or still serve) a purpose different than echolocation. It evolved because it improved the individual’s buoyancy for example — and it turned out it could be used for echolocation as well.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>hyperfocus</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Hyperfocus-of-the-week-Refraction-Evolution-and-Belugas.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Altruism and hobby spending</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Altruism-and-hobby-spending.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Ordinary People are Evil: and this from a very simple argumentation. It’s <em>our</em> moral duty to donate to charity the money otherwise spent on luxury.</p>
<p>Peter-Singer’s argument begins with the premise that we have a moral duty to assist in solving <em>very bad</em> problems, provided that we are capable of doing so. Are famine and poverty <em>very bad</em> things? Then you see where this is going.</p>
<p>Donating to charity serves as proxy for solving these <em>very bad</em> things — and, if it’s so easy to donate to them, why we choose, over and over again, to buy a cup of expensive coffee, or buy a car, or anything superfluous?</p>
<p>This is hard to refute. I could say that spending money as we see fit doesn’t make the average citizen <em>evil</em>: <em>evil</em> is the underlying system that coerces us to do so — a system which was not designed with this moral duty in mind.</p>
<p>What if superfluous things do serve a <em>purpose</em>? They often signalize power — think designer items — and might serve as a ‘social boost’ for the individual to eventually earn more. By earning more he is objectively more powerful when performing this moral duty.</p>
<p>Should this moral duty be seem as accumulative or be exercised daily to be fulfilled? Consider the example of a rich guy who never donate a single cent to charity, <em>but</em> just before he dies he distribute his whole wealth to charity institutions.</p>
<p>One could make the case that our moral duty is to accumulate the maximum possible wealth — to fulfill one’s wealth potential — enabling the donation of bigger sums in the future. See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earning_to_give">Earning to give</a>.</p>
<p>To make the example even more morally complex, let us assume the rich guy has done so, not because of his moral duty, but by pure spite of his sons neglecting him in the adulthood. The donation was more a moral lesson to his sons <em>than</em> a fulfillment of his moral duties.</p>
<p>Is the moral duty in our internal perception or in the sum objectively donated? Or in both?</p>
<p>These are the sort of questions I ask myself when translating the argument to our society. I do think is important to exercise frugality independent of social status. But how much to do while keeping oneself motivated, interesting and sane in the society? Luxury is also sometimes hard to detect — there are brands whose line between utility and luxury is blurred, hence what I often catch myself saying: “it’s more expensive, but I trust the brand X and I know it will probably last way longer than the cheaper one from brand Y.”</p>
<p>The line is so blurred that the perceived qualities of a given brand — a maintainable, reliable, durable product — are used as justification for its luxury. How far do theses supposedly quality attributes cover its higher price is up to debate.</p>
<p>“I justify drinking this fancy light-roasted Nicaragua coffee brewed using my ceramic v60 because, seriously, without coffee I can’t even <em>start</em> working.” This one hits home. Can I justify spending 10 times what some people have to eat in a fancy coffee so the gentleman me can <em>start</em> working… from home?</p>
<p>These are part of what I call hobby-spendings; the money I spent upgrading my mini recording studio belongs to this same category. They are definitely an exercise of luxury: I didn’t have to spend the amount I did. But does this make me evil?</p>
<p>In some sense, yes. However, hobbies provide me <em>purpose</em> and help me stay <em>sane</em>. These are arguably important functions; therefore, when we perceive the whole picture, an unmotivated me wouldn’t earn as much money as a motivated me. Is it then my fault that I need these little escapisms from daily life in order to properly function in society? Should I carry the moral burden of not fulfilling this moral duty alone? Or did society make me evil, or by society being evil am I bound to also be?</p>
<p>These are attempts of justification; but they are weak. Had I donated the money I spent in hobbies, society would have been better off — with the cost of me being a more uninteressant and unmotivated person. Is it a fair price to pay? Or is there a limit — a common sense limit — of how much you can spend in hobbies and still be morally fair?</p>
<p>Currently I draw the line based on a hobby enjoyment utility: if the purchase helps me enjoy the hobby more, then I justify spending more money on it. I know, I know, it’s so easy to <em>game</em> this artificial line, “Oh, I need one more guitar because.. because.. this one never goes out of tune! So I can use the time practicing and not tuning it!” Clearly a luxury-driven purchase I would say. Or maybe not? “hear me out, player X uses this guitar and listen to it for a second: it’s amazing. How can I even start recording my songs without having it?” Stop!</p>
<p>“I’ll buy jacket X because it protects me <em>good</em> against wind and cold. It costs more but I’ll be warm for the average 10 min per day I stay outside in the winter.”</p>
<p>“Oh look. That game is in sale in Steam! Let us buy it so we can play together for 2 hours and never touch it again.”</p>
<p>“I’ll gladly pay a bit more for this mayo, because the other tastes a bit odd.”</p>
<p>We have the luxury of spending money so freely; should we relinquish that and live as frugal as possible? Or should we delegate the moral burden to society? Or should we just take part in consumerism and live as usual — since it keep us sane?</p>
<p>Pledges like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giving_What_We_Can">Giving What We Can</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earning_to_give">Earning to give</a> are incomplete realizations of Effective altruism as proposed by Singer. They tackle the issue from the monetary perspective, but not from the internal agent perspective. Frugality can be a consequence of taking the pledge, but not instrumental for it.</p>
<p>Another aspect is how different is to donate to a charity and to donate to, let’s say, your mother who is in need? Why choose your mother, who let’s assume is not in risk of famine due to her support net, but need the money to sustain herself and be motivated? Is that a luxury spending — spending in your mother so that she can live better instead of spending to solve world famine?</p>
<p>Solving these <em>very bad</em> issues is a shared moral burden, which are best solved bottom-up one could argue. Does this legitimizes conquering countries whose management are inefficient in tackling the basic subsistent needs of the population? Crazy to think about this, that even war could be legitimized by this simple thinking exercise.</p>
<p>When we maximize one goal and forget about others — or the context where the goal is to be pursued — we get into the risk of the genie effect: there are many paths to realize a given goal, but the genie likes to fulfill the wish while also maximizes suffering for the wisher. I know, this is not to say that society would act as a genie; but it could! It’s a possibility one can’t ignore.</p>
<p>To completely delegate the moral burden to society is to float in the waves of its decisions. An inert life full of soma-like acceptance.</p>
<p>Morally just, morally incorrect.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Altruism-and-hobby-spending.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hey, just write and things will be eventually okay</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Hey-just-write-and-things-will-be-eventually-okay.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m still working heavily on the most difficult project I tackled so far: the project of a how to research. I see now, it’s incredibly difficult to maintain a system where critical thought, discussion, is incentivized. Just intaking information does not do any good; this is the realization I come to over and over again.</p>
<p>I want to contribute meaningfully to the world. Contribute to technologies that I’m convinced will change the world. I find the area of safe autonomous systems essential for this — and I can only do a good work here if I think out of the box. Emergent ideas.</p>
<p>So my systems should foment the creation of emergent ideas. I don’t want to make this piece a piece about how to achieve this, since the answer is still unclear to me. I do however think that I made some progress during these couple weeks.</p>
<p>I realized I put so much weight on details: <a href="../posts/2025-05-On-naming-notes.html">On naming notes</a> is the living prove. Of course, working on this project involve exploring the whole field of possibilities; nothing wrong here. However, experience has shown to me, that if you <em>just</em> work on a project — let it kneed itself — you will end up on systems that conformed best (or best enough) to the task at the hand.</p>
<p>Best in this case is heavily debatable. Normally what ends up happening is most friction points are filed out; if there’s an allowed path of least resistance it’ll get chosen eventually. And this is my grand master plan behind researching: I have to do it long enough. It’s <em>okay</em>, it’s fine if everything is slow, sometimes redundant in this first stage. Let it sit and do it long enough. You will find what works and what not.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, this can only work if the optimization goals are clear from the start. These are (1) ideate and discuss: see the gaps and generate novel solutions for standing research questions; and (2) extract artifacts: a repository build in such a way that you can just “pluck” articles, posts or any deliverable. It should benefit from compound effects — pay us interest.</p>
<p>I just want to get these goals right from the start. As long what I am doing are aligned with that and my gut feeling say that what I am doing is correct, then keep it. If I have a hunch that something can be improved or would lead to a goal being deviated: discuss it. Write about, remember Writing is Thinking.</p>
<p>I guess this is what I wanted to hear, since I got a mind-freeing feeling after writing this. The task at hand is daunting. It’s enormous and open-endend: I understand why it can be overwhelming. However, you have implemented a system that is already providing utility; and you have also a support net if things go south.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Hey-just-write-and-things-will-be-eventually-okay.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On naming notes</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-On-naming-notes.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Interestingly enough, I already worked on this project in October of 2024. I mentioned a link from Andy-Matuschak where he discussed his naming scheme.</p>
<p>Unfortunately I didn’t delve much into the topic — and maybe that’s why it came back hunting me today. But let’s jump back to one of Andy’s statements:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>These [the note titles] are often declarative or imperative phrases making a strong claim. This puts pressure on me to adequately support the claim in the body.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I noticed that I currently don’t do that. I think it could compromise finding the note again in a later moment. And this is a big turn off: if you don’t find the note again, you end up with many notes touching the same problematic but without any connection. A good naming system should also optimize for finding the note again!</p>
<p>But that’s not a comprehensive critique of this naming scheme. Not at all. I’ll get back to it eventually.</p>
<p>Another technique he mentioned is to use questions as titles (something I also heavily considered). A question forces the need for an answer; and sometimes that’s exactly what we wants. Thus naming notes based on this concept makes sense from the perspective of the outcome we want and the way we think — asking questions, hypotheses and looking up in the answer space is second-nature when are trying to solve a problem.</p>
<p>One common realization is that concept notes get us only <em>so</em> far. We need middle ground notes that symbolize their work-in-progress nature — they are thoughts being built or relevant thoughts from others that we want to preserve for future discussions.</p>
<p>I also don’t think it’s <em>inherently</em> bad if the note has less re-discoverability (is that a word?). It’s okay if some notes only resurface when you are in a given mental state.</p>
<p>So the question I ask is which naming rules lead to better thinking? The name of the note is important because it <em>constrains</em> the scope of the note. And the scope we work on <em>constrains</em> the types of connections we can make and the emergent novel thoughts we can potentially make.</p>
<p>Balancing context is key when designing notes.</p>
<section id="notes-that-enable-better-thinking" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notes-that-enable-better-thinking">Notes that enable better thinking</h2>
<p>On one side we have notes that are clearly bound to a concept, to a reference note, to a day, to a month. There’s no or little ambiguity on how to call them. On the other side, when working on the project of understanding a concept better — the pros, the cons, the historical influx of ideas that shaped it — we want to rely on a set of guidelines to shape it into a serviceable state: one that incentivizes discussion, connection and convolution with our minds.</p>
<p>I like the idea of writing the strongest context cue first on the title. For a more fleeting note/essay this manifests in the form of a date, or a simplified version of it with just the year and the month — see this note for an example. It elegantly attaches the quality of being “fleeting” to it without tags or any special mechanisms.</p>
<section id="an-use-case" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-use-case">An use case</h3>
<p>To shape this idea even further I’ll mention the use case of annotating a academic paper — since it’s activity I’m currently doing a lot. I want to be able to put the author’s idea in contrast to other authors; and also preserve it for future instances, in which I want to retrieve this knowledge.</p>
<p>For that I am often relying on implicit indexes: if the given reference contributes to a new challenge for a given topic, I link it to a note called “Challenges of [topic]”. I call it implicit index because the indexation is happening <em>implicitly</em>, via backlinks: if I want to retrieve the whole mapping I go this “challenges” note and see all its backlinks.</p>
<p>I like this; it’s flexible enough and I’m not repeating myself.</p>
<p>So from here we start to see the emergence of a new type of note. It’s not a concept <em>per se</em>, but it is a <em>research</em> about this topic.</p>
<p>They’re researches in their simplest form: state of art researches. Naming them is straightforward: I see the pattern emerging of combining a <em>strong noun</em> with a <em>topic</em>. Another example is <em>Use cases for [topic]</em>.</p>
<p>There’s two aspects of a research that are relevant: the backlinks — who is contributing to and using this research; and its content: which patterns emerge from it? Which other sub-researches emerge from it? And here it becomes evident its “open-ended” nature. We will hardly know if the research is completely <em>resolved</em> — of course, sometimes it’s possible; however, more often than not, the best we could do is give our best shot based on what we currently know.</p>
<p>They are not <em>everlasting</em>: Researches are fluid!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="researches-are-fluid" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="researches-are-fluid">Researches are fluid</h2>
<p>Opposed to atomic concepts with a clear story and application behind, researches are open-ended by nature. Even the research question behind it can change and even become stale, obsolete, get refined, get expanded.</p>
<p>A new contribution can come and completely change your understanding and previous notion/answer to it. And this is <em>by design</em>. Therefore, a good system for representing them should also consider its fluid nature.</p>
<p>But how to name them?</p>
<p>As discussed, for simpler notes the pattern of a strong noun + topic can be helpful. However, for the vast majority of research questions we need a bit more variety in the expression. Fact is that I am still learning how to do it well. I still haven’t converged into an adequate method for doing that; oftentimes I name it as questions — closely resembling the research question, with hows, whats and so on; in others I think a statement fits better.</p>
<p>Maybe this lack of consistency is not entirely bad. But it’s a consequence of how this particular research is more commonly expressed out of there. Nevertheless, this is still an open topic to me.</p>
</section>
<section id="claims-as-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="claims-as-notes">claims as notes</h2>
<p>I support the idea from Andy-Matuschak about creating notes for strong claims. I like that these notes can be naturally used mid sentences due to the natural way it’s formulated.</p>
<p>More broader than that, I argue for creating notes for every discussion-worthy claim. If a note is strong, then it’s helpful to extract in its own note. You might even bind the reference as its main context like “[claim] by [author], [year]”.</p>
<p>To help <em>contain</em> the messier nature of having multiple notes, it’s helpful to use Indexes or Outline-Notes.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-On-naming-notes.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Learning about anarchism</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Learning-about-anarchism.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I found out I have a really shallow understanding of Anarchism. It’s the same old thing over and over: we think we have a minimum understanding of a topic — enough to know about when someone’s talking about it — but we actually have a nuanced view of it from school, friends or you name it.</p>
<p>It might be enough to understand what your local ancap friend is speaking, but not nearly scrapping the tip of the iceberg of all the collective thought that was put on this project.</p>
<p>It’s just this illusion of having at least a small understanding of it that bothers me a lot — where all this confidence in my beliefs come from? Out of nowhere, out of blue.</p>
<p>I’m not saying I am proponent of anarchism — I mean, I just said I barely understand it — but I see the value in having the discussion and understanding where the thinkers are coming from. People way smarter than me dealt with this issues and arrived at the conclusion that <em>this way</em> of seeing things could fit the world better. It could be a solution to the failed project we live in.</p>
<p>Once again, my one-sided friend of this Digital-Panopticon, Stephen West from Philosophize-This! spoke to me closely — around 1.5 hours, during my last failed attempt of a half marathon.<sup>1</sup></p>
<p>I set up his 4 episodes about anarchism and had the goal of understanding it at least a <em>bit</em> better.</p>
<p>I’ll start with the last thing I remember: what I understood so far about anarchism was <em>actually</em> Anarcho-Capitalism. But more on this later.</p>
<p>I should be careful when defining each of these terms. He explains it’s sometimes hard for the proponents to agree on definitions and the core principles around anarchism. This is a feature and not a bug: this “free” way of thinking leads naturally to less constrains on the terminology. The disagreements are often in the implementation details; however they could also emerge from completely different schools of thought: basing the mediation device on the market opposed to the human, for example.</p>
<section id="whats-in-common" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-in-common">What’s in common</h2>
<p>But one thing seems to be constant: Authority-has-to-be-justified. The Representative-Democracy should justify itself for its continued existence; or less abstractly, the major of your city: he should also have to justify his position of power.</p>
<p>This makes sense to me; why collectively pay somebody to sit there and do things that neither his peers nor he throughly understands! Managing such a complex system, with thousand, hundred thousands, millions of people is simply impossible. To have people with such a strong concentrated responsibility (and privileges) boggles the mind.</p>
<p>Their answer? A bottom-up Federated-Society based on Direct-Democracy. Groups of people with similar interests form naturally — and it makes sense for each interested party to be able to decide matters that impact them (and opt out from matters that are irrelevant to them)</p>
<p>These groups can become part of larger federations if they choose to. But the key distinction is the flexibility: they can opt-out easily when the conditions are not beneficial anymore.</p>
<p>They can also “lend” power to someone chosen to represent the group. He is, however, merely a proxy to the opinions of the group — since votes are casted directly and not being decided by the head of it. The flexible opt-out mechanism behaves similarly here: if the person is not adequately representing the group anymore, he can be removed from the position.</p>
<p>People argue that this horizontal organization emerges naturally from humans. Things start to go south, however, when societies grow bigger. The illusion is then sold to us, that we need to rely on bigger and complex mechanism to hold “democracy” together.</p>
<p>He also mentions the distinction between Anarcho-Capitalism — the market-orient one — and Anarchism-Communism. However, I won’t try to differentiate both of them. I’m just now on the tip of the icerbeg of all that is out there.</p>
<p>Some names I have to read more are Noam-Chomski, Errico-Malatesta, Peter-Gelderloos.</p>
</section>
<section id="and-i-divagate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="and-i-divagate">And I divagate</h2>
<p>In reality, more often than not, representatives — that are to be the proxies for the people — become proxies for the corporations: they act in a biased way and not on the interest of the electors. It’s so common that’s nauseating.</p>
<p>Why it’s so <em>hard</em> to implement alternatives to that.</p>
<p>When we are immersed in this environment, born and raised, it’s difficult to see the way <em>out</em> of the cage.</p>
<p>Capitalism or Technofeudalism or whatever this state we are currently in is going to be defined and called is pervasive in every spectrum of being human nowadays.</p>
</section>
<section id="i-wonder" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="i-wonder">I wonder</h2>
<p>How close the concepts of a Federated-Society is to a Federated-Architecture — that is a decentralized architecture where Autonomous-Systems collaborate towards a goal.</p>
<p>In some sense, it’s really similar: the approach is also bottom-up. We define the goal and the systems come up with Instrumental Goals for performing it. Swap systems for a group of 100 people and the goal to being able to eat and suddenly we have someone opening a kitchen.</p>
<p>Do the research in both areas — anthropology/philosophy and engineering — converge somehow? If so, how so? Federated Society and Federated Autonomous Systems - What is the overlap</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>A 15k. Failed in the sense of it not being a half marathon, but not a failure. Don’t get me wrong: I am really grateful of taking the time for taking care of myself :)↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>MCS</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Learning-about-anarchism.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2025-05 Research Dump</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Research-Dump.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<ol type="1">
<li>2025-05-SOA-and-MAS-Paradigms-applied-to-Reconfigurable-Manufacturing-Systems</li>
<li>2025-05-Understanding-Traditional-Safety-Engineering</li>
<li>2025-05-My-Research-so-Far</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research-dump</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Research-Dump.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Designing for Reading Comprehension</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Designing-for-Reading-Comprehension.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<ol type="1">
<li>Let us make the distinction between comprehending and knowing.</li>
<li>Knowing a topic refers to possessing information about it — being aware that it exists. There’s no requirement regarding the depth of understanding — its meaning or applicability.</li>
<li>Comprehending requires deep understanding of a topic — its meaning, implications, and surrounding aspects are well understood.</li>
<li>Comprehension is a <em>much</em> better goal when designing a reading system.</li>
<li>Just being superficially aware of a topic is <em>not</em> enough for most purposes. We can’t truly discuss such topics; we can only <em>fake</em> a discussion.</li>
<li>Systems designed for knowledge lack the ability to foster real thinking. Engineering courses, academic programs, and schools are prime examples of what happens when systems are designed for mere knowledge.</li>
<li>You end up with information, but it’s disconnected — dangling — with no roots in your existing conceptual base. Any gentle breeze can pull it away. Suddenly, we’re not even aware of it anymore.</li>
<li>I think about all the concepts I learned during school and engineering; they didn’t stick. At a foundational level, only the things I kept using and was more motivated about endured.</li>
<li>One might say that it’s not the job of universities or schools to teach comprehension of these topics. But then — whose job is it? Do we have to figure it out ourselves? We spend so <em>much</em> time in these places — really, a big chunk of our lives — and we’re left with blankness, or at best, a slightly less blank view of reality.</li>
<li>Comprehension is, therefore, key. All meaningful learning systems should have this as their goal.</li>
</ol>
<section id="how-to-foster-comprehension-in-a-learning-system" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-foster-comprehension-in-a-learning-system">How to foster comprehension in a learning system?</h2>
<section id="the-limitations-of-the-brain" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-limitations-of-the-brain">The limitations of the brain</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>We must recognize that we are designing systems for humans — humans with brains, and brains have limitations.</li>
<li>I’ll base my comparisons on personal experience as a human being learning how to learn. So take this as a critical limitation of the discussion.</li>
<li>Still, I claim that other brains behave similarly.</li>
<li>Brains have a limited “comprehension bus factor”: expecting too much comprehension at once often leads to frustration.</li>
<li>Brains learn <em>only</em> when we add a new concept on top of a well-established base. Adding many dangling concepts at once is, again, a major source of frustration.</li>
<li>Therefore, concepts should be <em>heavily</em> interconnected.</li>
<li>Simply regurgitating knowledge is boring. It creates the illusion of comprehension and benefits neither the speaker nor the listener.</li>
<li>Concepts should be discussed. Through discussion, you discover gaps in your understanding and test the strength of your conceptual roots — where they are strong and where they’re weak.</li>
<li>Brains are not naturally great at abstract thinking. It’s not that they can’t do it — on the contrary — but I argue that concrete instantiations of knowledge (via examples or mappings) are key to truly understanding something.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="putting-all-principles-together" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="putting-all-principles-together">Putting all principles together</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>A learning system should be designed to maximize discussion of ideas.</li>
<li>Discussion is the primary process that generates comprehension.</li>
<li>Through discussion, you connect ideas.</li>
<li>But merely connecting ideas — as proposed in Active-Ideation — is not the ideal goal.</li>
<li>An idea might be linked to thousands of others and still be dangling — barely surviving in our memory.</li>
<li>This has happened with many concepts I often relate to others. But the connection is superficial — since neither concept was deeply understood. It becomes a shallow link and sometimes even detrimental, as we see links but can’t recall where they come from.</li>
<li>Nor is recall improvement — as proposed by Progressive-Summarization — an ideal goal.</li>
<li>I agree that notes should be designed to be recallable by your future self.</li>
<li>But this alone doesn’t serve as a good goal for a learning system.</li>
<li>It doesn’t differentiate between superficial knowledge and comprehension. Your brain will quickly learn how to game the system — giving you the <em>illusion</em> of comprehension because you’re “doing it right.”</li>
<li>You get stuck thinking, “The results will come if I keep doing this every day for years.” But you don’t <em>see</em> them — yet.</li>
<li>This falls into the Collector’s Fallacy: you’re conflating the collection of knowledge with comprehension. As we’ve seen, these are very different things.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="a-practical-example-annotating-books-and-papers" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-practical-example-annotating-books-and-papers">A practical example: annotating books and papers</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>What’s the value of a highlight? “To mark the important parts of a text,” you say.</li>
<li>But why do that? “So I can remember the important parts.” But how does a highlight actually help with that?</li>
<li>Here is where the argument starts to fall apart. “If I read the highlight, I’ll remember the key part of the text and won’t need to reread the whole thing!” Wrong. Try it — or maybe you already have. Take a dense paper and highlight the key parts. Do this regularly. You’ll soon find yourself highlighting large blocks of text — because there are so many “key parts” and unknowns you need to revisit later.</li>
<li>Now return to the text a few weeks later. Did the highlights help you remember the key parts? I doubt it. It’s just a mess.</li>
<li>Highlights are not for remembering information! Not even close. Don’t be unfair to yourself — acknowledge the limitations of your brain.</li>
<li>Highlights are, first and foremost, visual cues. “Cues for what?” For marking that a <em>discussion</em> took place. When no discussion happened, no highlight — simple as that.</li>
<li>If you return to the text in a week and reread your discussion points instead, you’ll immediately be back where you left off. You’re up to date on the relationship between the text <em>and</em> your more deeply-rooted concepts.</li>
<li>If no discussion happened, you didn’t understand the text. That’s the key point.</li>
<li>It’s not your job to maintain a comprehensive version of the author’s ideas in your knowledge base. That’s the job of Wikipedia, LLMs, or textbooks.</li>
<li>Your job is to bring your <em>own perspective</em> into the equation. This aligns with Active-Ideation, but the focus is not just on relationships — it’s on discussions.</li>
</ol>
<p>Discussion-is-the-Main-Goal!</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-05-Designing-for-Reading-Comprehension.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2025-04 Research Dump</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-04-Research-Dump.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="goals-for-2025-04" class="level2">

<ol type="1">
<li>2025-04-G1: write a draft of a position paper about dynamic risk management in flexible production systems</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="a-new-approach" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-new-approach">A new approach</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>I started dividing the researches into individual components. Every of them deserves a survey by its own merit — since it’s extremely difficult to survey all of them at once, based on a broad, general query.</li>
<li>The main consequence of this approach is a more interconnected research, relying on backlinks.</li>
<li>I <em>still</em> don’t have a good solution for the ingestion process: <a href="../posts/Continuous-Research.html">Continuous-Research</a>, the collection of methods I compiled for maintaining and expanding knowledge, is lacking in this regard.
<ol type="1">
<li>In particular, I tend to lose focus. I’m reading a piece, and suddenly I’m caught in another topic — almost a requirement for me to move forward in the original goal.</li>
<li>What I end up having is many researches that, at least, overlap, and more often than I would like to admit, are completely redundant.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Another challenge I currently have is linking researches with references.
<ol type="1">
<li>For each piece of reference I read, I write a note that’s referenceable to a <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Bib%5CTeX"> item by its citekey. There I add my notes and highlights.</li>
<li>Often a reference contributes to a research and I keep asking myself the same question “should I add a related-work-like summary into the research or not?” If yes, what about Dont-Repeat-Yourself? What about a possible desync. between ref and the research?</li>
<li>I know, I know. It’s stupid, but that’s where my brain goes. This generates friction and stresses me out.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>I also would like to keep working on research dumps — public pages that summarizes what I did during the month.
<ol type="1">
<li>I hate that this new approach (more segregated researches) lead me to just linking this file with many non-public researches. They are not public, because they are mess of citations, half-baked thoughts.. simply not ready for someone to read!</li>
</ol></li>
<li>I’m working on this paper: The Role of Dynamic Risk Management in Flexible Production Systems
<ol type="1">
<li>This page is currently <em>not</em> available for the public. The reason is that it is a big mess at the current state.</li>
<li>I’m also afraid of misunderstanding an author’s work deeply. Even if it’s a preprint, I want to keep a high-enough standard of publication.</li>
<li>However, I’m thinking about how to deploy incremental preprints of my work (is this a thing?)</li>
<li>Also: now I clearly stated my focus: I want to understand DRM for flexible production systems (still unsure about the precise term to use)</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="continuous-safety-assurance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="continuous-safety-assurance">Continuous-Safety-Assurance</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="patelEnhancingContinuousRisk2024">@patelEnhancingContinuousRisk2024</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="khanDynamicRiskManagement2016">@khanDynamicRiskManagement2016</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="schneiderDynamicRiskManagement2024">@schneiderDynamicRiskManagement2024</span>: add missing refs</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="dynamic-risk-assessment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dynamic-risk-assessment">Dynamic-Risk-Assessment</h2>
</section>
<section id="safe-reconfiguration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="safe-reconfiguration">Safe-Reconfiguration</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="kloseBuildingBlocksFlexible2021">@kloseBuildingBlocksFlexible2021</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="pelzerConduciveDesignSafety2022">@pelzerConduciveDesignSafety2022</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="hillenPlugandProduceSafelyEndtoEnd2022">@hillenPlugandProduceSafelyEndtoEnd2022</span></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="representing-reconfiguration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="representing-reconfiguration">Representing-Reconfiguration</h2>
</section>
<section id="uncertainty-assessment-of-safety-evidences" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="uncertainty-assessment-of-safety-evidences">Uncertainty-Assessment-of-Safety-Evidences</h2>
</section>
<section id="surveys-misc" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="surveys-misc">Surveys Misc</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="raveendranComprehensiveReviewDynamic2022">@raveendranComprehensiveReviewDynamic2022</span></li>
<li><span class="citation" data-cites="rajabliSoftwareVerificationValidation2021">@rajabliSoftwareVerificationValidation2021</span></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research-dump</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-04-Research-Dump.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A small survey on managing your documents locally</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-03-A-small-survey-on-managing-your-documents-locally.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="brief" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="brief">brief</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>I’m in a dire need of a solution to manage my personal documents: letters and all artifacts necessary for tax declaration.</li>
<li>It’s essential that I can host it myself on my server. I want to own the data.</li>
<li>I want the trust and audit that comes with FOSS, so I’ll limit myself to solutions that are FOSS.</li>
<li>It must support some level of automation: when I upload a new file it should offer automatic tagging, description, the stuff I’m too lazy to type out.</li>
<li>Eventually, I would like to plug a scanner in an automated workflow: I scan, and the printer should interact with this service somehow. I have to find out what’s the common name for this interaction and which protocols are used — scanner send the attachment as email? Or is it some kind of API?</li>
<li>In respect to the methodology of this survey I will put it frankly: I gave myself 1h30min to find and set up a solution; so I’ll just google and analyze the top results. I have a pile of documents next to me that I need to get rid of before lunch 😅</li>
<li>It should be actively maintained — so last commit in max. late 2024</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="matches" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="matches">matches</h2>
<section id="paperless" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paperless">Paperless</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>This project has been around since 2015, and there’s lots of people using it. For some reason, it’s really popular in Germany – maybe someone over there can clue me in as to why? [2]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Why is it popular on the country that a service sends you 3 letters just for you to be able to log in in their app? No clue haha</p>
<p>And it’s archived since 2021. It provides the workflow with the printer/scanner I wanted by it scanning to a FTP server – with the requirement that the scanner should also support this option.</p>
<p>From their GitHub [1] I came across Mayan [2] which <em>is</em> actively maintained. But it seems really bulky and more aimed at enterprise users, at least this was my first impression.</p>
</section>
<section id="docspell" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="docspell">Docspell</h3>
<p>Docspell [3] seems nice. It supports these kinds of automated workflows by means of a NLP library. Let me look in the issues.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I’ve just toyed around with the latest llamafile release and I have to say: I think we are at the point where it starts to be feasible to have a LLM running locally for auto tagging on import. – [1, Issue 1996]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is interesting. A LLM service would kind of solve the issue, wouldn’t it? Just a simple file server and a local LLM extracting tags and description would suffice. In respect to that (1) I have no idea about the quality gain of an workflow with just LLM and one using NLP; and (2) my server is weak to run LLMs locally – and I don’t want sensitive letters becoming part of a training data set. Also, a LLM+file server-based workflow would cost me <em>way</em> more time to implement decently. Thus, it makes more sense to go with an off-the-shelf solution.</p>
<p>It supports <a href="https://docspell.org/docs/feed/">different ingestion workflows</a>, e.g.&nbsp;documents send to an e-mail folder are automatically processed. So the scanner must support sending e-mails. A CLI is also provided with utilities like watching a folder for new documents and automatically picking them for processing. This is excellent.</p>
<p>It also provides the option to store the files directly in the FS – no DB. This is also good to have if I don’t want to manage an extra service for the database. From what I understood I can just use the FS as file backend and an H2 file as metadata backend. Exactly what I was looking for.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="testing-docspell" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="testing-docspell">Testing Docspell</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Using their <a href="https://github.com/docspell/docker/blob/main/docker-compose/docker-compose.yml">default docker-compose</a> I get 1.34gb memory footprint. That’s a bit too high for my taste. Most of it is due to <a href="https://github.com/docspell/docker/blob/main/docker-compose/docker-compose.yml">Apache Solr</a> – do I need it to run Docspell?
<ol type="1">
<li>It’s possible to use postgres as the full text backend. I don’t think I need Solr for that, at least for my home use cases.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>I will leave it running for the day and watch for spikes while idle.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="wondering" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wondering">Wondering</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>I think there’s the opportunity for a simpler system: a markdown file linked to each attachment with the metadata stored in the frontmatter as YAML. It can be stored alongside the files and extensions/utilities just need to parse the YAML metadata and not integrate to any tool.</li>
<li>The more I think about it the less I want to manage <em>another</em> service for storing files. I just need the files in the FS of my home server with the metadata stored alongside. Maybe there is already a solution for that.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1]: <a href="https://github.com/the-paperless-project/paperless">GitHub - the-paperless-project/paperless: Scan, index, and archive all of your paper documents</a></p>
<p>[2]: <a href="https://gitlab.com/mayan-edms/mayan-edms/-/tree/master">Files · master · Mayan EDMS / Mayan EDMS · GitLab</a></p>
<p>[3]: <a href="https://github.com/eikek/docspell">GitHub - eikek/docspell: Assist in organizing your piles of documents, resulting from scanners, e-mails and other sources with miminal effort.</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>done</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-03-A-small-survey-on-managing-your-documents-locally.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Heuristics to reduce the chaos in life</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Heuristics-to-reduce-the-chaos-in-life.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m a big fan of simple things that abstract a lot of complexity and add value to my life. However, it’s difficult to find them unless they come from generational knowledge—the kind of wisdom your parents passed down, which you follow out of habit built over the years.</p>
<p>A good generational example is <em>waking up early</em>—and, of course, its counterpart, <em>going to sleep early</em>. This simple heuristic translates to improvements in many areas of your life: (1) you have more <em>work time</em>, which increases productivity; (2) you have more <em>hobby time</em>, which boosts happiness; (3) you can see the sun 🌞 early in the morning, which brings numerous health benefits [1]. And these are just the surface-level benefits.</p>
<p>Another example that has worked for me—and one I had to learn on my own—is maintaining <em>buffers</em>. Finances can be chaotic, and sometimes you have to pay for unplanned expenses. Part of life is that some taxes or cost centers—like a car—demand lump-sum payments that are hard to foresee. An easy solution is to have a buffer account. Every month, money gets added to it, and any extra funds at the end of the month can also go there. This practice gives every dollar or euro a purpose, another helpful heuristic that isn’t always easy to learn.</p>
<p>These measures might seem simplistic or even obvious—as if everyone already does them—but I appreciate them more and more because they bring immense value without much upkeep.</p>
<p>They are flexible enough to be domain-independent. The concept of buffers is useful in a multitude of applications: finances, computer science, inventory management, and more. Once you learn and implement them, you feel that a once complex problem has become much more manageable. That peace of mind is priceless.</p>
<p>I wonder what other helpful (perhaps hidden) heuristics I follow every day without even noticing. I wonder what else is out there that could heavily simplify my life but that I simply haven’t come across or acknowledged.</p>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<p>[1]: <a href="https://ai.hubermanlab.com/clip?sids=chunk_49345">Morning Sunlight Benefits | Ask Huberman Lab</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Heuristics-to-reduce-the-chaos-in-life.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Essay-based Learning</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Essay-based-Learning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Thoughts arrive in an unordered manner. This is an issue for anyone trying to learn about different concepts—especially when multiple ideas are explored simultaneously. Learning about a forest, for example, may lead to deeper inquiry into trees, leaves, or, even more complexly, the animals living there. Everything is open to deeper understanding, but knowing when to stop subdividing or when to explore the breadth of related concepts is a difficult skill to develop.</p>
<p>Much of my writing touches on this problem: How can I navigate this body of knowledge while remaining sane and still achieving productive results? There must be at least some degree of <em>systematic</em> organization. At the same time, care must be taken not to overdo it—too much system, too much framework, and it begins to hinder research itself.</p>
<p>One approach I find particularly useful is thinking through writing. The process of composing an essay helps me clarify my thoughts and identify misconceptions or gaps in my understanding. I call this approach <em>Essay-based Learning</em>: writing small, opinionated essays that synthesize my current understanding of a topic. These are not just Wikipedia-like descriptions of concepts but rather focused pieces addressing specific research questions. Less formal than an academic article, yet structured enough to serve as a foundation for one.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Essay-based-Learning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2025-03 Research Dump</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-03-Research-Dump.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="problem-statement" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-statement">Problem statement</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>I started researching the topic of runtime safety management of Machine Learning (ML) components as a PhD candidate at the RPTU.</li>
<li>They are often a black box with low understandability. This leads to variable uncertainty during the runtime.</li>
<li>Current Risk-Assessment processes relies on worst-case operational assumptions made on the design phase</li>
<li>Therefore we need a way to make the shift of certain aspects of Safety-Assurance to runtime. See Risk-Assessment-at-Runtime</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="currently-doing" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="currently-doing">Currently doing</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Reading the previous work from the commonly cited researchers in the field</li>
<li>Reviewing relevant terminology, standards and concepts</li>
<li>Mapping conferences, workshops, journals</li>
<li>2025-03-The-Roles-of-Uncertainty-Risk-and-Hazard-in-Dynamic-Assessment</li>
<li><a href="../posts/Essay-based-Learning.html">Essay-based-Learning</a></li>
<li>2025-03-Safety-Assurance-of-RMS</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="reading-list" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reading-list">Reading list</h2>
<section id="haupt-and-liggesmeyer-2019" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="haupt-and-liggesmeyer-2019">Haupt and Liggesmeyer, 2019</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="Haupt2019166">@Haupt2019166</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Autonomous-Systems operating in an unknown, dynamic and unstructured safety-critical environment requires different techniques for Safety-Assurance.</li>
<li>The paper’s contribution is a rule-based runtime safety monitoring component that observes system’s deviations</li>
<li>In the design phase the system is decomposed in its services – borrowing from SOA – is able to perform. For each combination of <em>service deviation</em> and context (operational mode, like fully autonomous, and environmental info during operation) a HARA is performed. See Table 1 below.</li>
<li>A risk monitoring service outputs a result akin to ASIL but for the target domain.</li>
<li>They evaluated in a Tractor-Implement-Automation scenario, which is a Reconfiguration scenario where the configuration of the agricultural implement can be changed by the vehicle itself – autonomously. This is really cool. Similar to I4.0.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/Pasted-image-20250318154738.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Source: Haupt, 2019</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="patel-and-liggesmeyer-2021" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="patel-and-liggesmeyer-2021">Patel and Liggesmeyer, 2021</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="patelMachineLearningBased2021">@patelMachineLearningBased2021</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>He is using Support Vector Machine to implement Dynamic-Risk-Assessment at runtime for the Autonomous-Vehicles domain. “DRA-SVM”</li>
<li>SVM is a Supervised-Learning technique, therefore he needed to manually select the features to be monitored</li>
<li>His model gets as input the vehicle status data (acceleration, braking) and outputs Severity and Controllability rating</li>
<li>It was validated using an Adaptive-Cruise-Control CARLA simulation. Both training and test data also come from the simulation. So theoretical applicability only.</li>
<li>He mentions as future work the possible addition of a decision-making component that gets the outputs from his model and makes the decision of, I guess, reducing speed or braking.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="hartsell-et-al.-2021" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hartsell-et-al.-2021">Hartsell et al., 2021</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="hartsellReSonAteRuntimeRisk2021">@hartsellReSonAteRuntimeRisk2021</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>RESONATE uses probabilistic models and conditional relationships derived from the BTD formalism to dynamically assess the risk in a situation – not quite rule-based.</li>
<li>It takes information from monitoring systems — which can be ML components — and sensor information</li>
<li>It relies on an extended BTD with probability information – output from the design phase</li>
<li>The component in the current form only outputs likelihood and <em>not</em> <em>severity</em></li>
<li><em>Uncertainty</em> is <em>also</em> not an output of RESONATE</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="reich-and-trapp-2020" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reich-and-trapp-2020">Reich and Trapp, 2020</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="reichSINADRAFrameworkAssurable2020">@reichSINADRAFrameworkAssurable2020</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>SINADRA is a framework encompassing risk analysis in both the design phase and runtime</li>
<li>Design phase includes synthesis of the runtime model</li>
<li>Main contribution is to get Residual-Risk at the runtime; claims previous work didn’t do that</li>
<li>Runtime model is a Bayesian-Network (BN) — therefore, model based — which get the intended EGO behaviour as input and outputs Residual-Risk + Uncertainty. This data can then be consumed by a decision making component – and then redirected to a Proactive-Risk-Control component e.g.</li>
<li>No evaluation is given</li>
<li>Explicit handling of uncertainty—from perception through to risk assessment</li>
<li>Similar to Patel, but Patel outputs Severity + Likelihood, if I’m not mistaken</li>
<li>Safety assurance is a key challenge; paper outlines the need to integrate the synthesis of the BN models into a systematic safety engineering process</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="kläes-et-al.-2021" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kläes-et-al.-2021">Kläes et al., 2021</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="klaesHandlingUncertaintiesDataDriven2021">@klaesHandlingUncertaintiesDataDriven2021</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>They are applying Uncertainty-Wrappers – additional models that enrich a DDM with Uncertainty information – in a DRM framework</li>
<li>They implemented an RSS validation scenario, in which the friction is considered to be dynamic and a source of uncertainty for estimating the Safe Distance.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="ertle-et-al.-2012" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ertle-et-al.-2012">Ertle et al., 2012</h3>
<p>Paper: <span class="citation" data-cites="ertleUtilizingDynamicHazard2012">@ertleUtilizingDynamicHazard2012</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>They use a database of Safety-Principles – specific known hazard causes – to assess risks.
<ol type="1">
<li>They mentioned the example of a plastic spoon approaching a burning candle. Toxic vapors evolve and the or the spoon starts to burn.</li>
<li>Therefore, one can conclude that heated plastic material can – they use <em>always</em> here, but I’m not so sure – generate toxic vapor or starts to burn.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The use case is an autonomous robot driving in a production plant. Every second (1Hz) they perform the process of (1) gathering environment data, (2) building the action plan – the set of the possible movement outcomes, (3) performing the Risk-Assessment with the method described in 1 and (4) executing the plan. (See Fig 1 for a really badly-drawn schematic)</li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/Pasted-image-20250318161830.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Fig 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="leite-et-al." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leite-et-al.">Leite et al.</h3>
<p>Papers: <span class="citation" data-cites="leiteSafetyAssuranceAutonomous2017">@leiteSafetyAssuranceAutonomous2017</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="leite2018dynamic">@leite2018dynamic</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="leite2019dynamic">@leite2019dynamic</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>the paper extends the previous work <span class="citation" data-cites="leiteSafetyAssuranceAutonomous2017">@leiteSafetyAssuranceAutonomous2017</span> by implementing a runtime risk assessment approach for autonomous and cooperative MCPS</li>
<li>Configurations are certified at design-time and attributed a SIL to dynamic decision-making.</li>
<li>For their use case – Patient-Controlled-Analgesia – smart alarm and automated interventions can be realized. The challenge is the insufficient context awareness and a lack of reasoning capabilities to deduce the current risk.</li>
<li>each configuration, pre-certified with a ConSert Tree Tree, is monitored in real time</li>
<li>Combined with ConSerts, it’s possible to continuously check the matching between current top-level Safety-Guarantees of the MCPS – Which can be subjected to Reconfiguration – and the current top-level safety requirement on the other.
<ol type="1">
<li>That means, (1) we can go from the selected configuration – which is specified during design time – and (2) analyze if the Safety-Guarantees are sufficient – which can be provided by ConSerts.</li>
<li>I wonder what is the corresponding term of Safety Guarantee from ISO 26262?</li>
</ol></li>
<li>A Bayesian-Network is used to calculate a configuration-dependent risk metric based on sensor data and expert-defined parameters</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="laxman-et-al." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="laxman-et-al.">Laxman et al.</h3>
<p>Papers: <span class="citation" data-cites="laxman2020u-map">@laxman2020u-map</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Proposes a reference map – U-map – for handling uncertainties.</li>
<li>It maps uncertainties with Hazards – which then can be mapped to Safety-Measures</li>
<li>Development of the U-map happens in the design phase.</li>
<li>A probabilistic model Bayesian-Network was used for runtime update</li>
<li>It mentions the possibility of the map being used as knowledge base for frameworks like MAPE-K feedback loops with the goal of analyzing the uncertainty and executing identified mitigation steps.</li>
<li>The use case presented was a production scenario where e.g.&nbsp;a mobile robot can be a hazard for a human.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="schneider-et-al." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="schneider-et-al.">Schneider et al.</h3>
<p>Papers: <span class="citation" data-cites="schneiderDynamicRiskManagement2024">@schneiderDynamicRiskManagement2024</span></p>
<p>Papers: <span class="citation" data-cites="schneider2010conditional">@schneider2010conditional</span>, <span class="citation" data-cites="schneiderApproachingRuntimeTrust2011">@schneiderApproachingRuntimeTrust2011</span></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Conditional Safety Certificates (ConSerts) are introduced to facilitate Dynamic-Risk-Assessment.
<ol type="1">
<li>ConSerts map safety property types of required and provided services</li>
<li>Specified in boolean logic similarly to CFTs – with gates and direct edges.</li>
<li>Allows associating runtime evidence to safety guarantees, which are associated with a SIL</li>
<li>I feel I need a more concrete example to better understand this concept</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Contributes to ideas of utilizing ConSerts to Support Trust</li>
<li>Why Conserts don’t support trust by default and must be extended?
<ol type="1">
<li>Because they don’t support trust certificates – considering security <em>and</em> the full spectrum of dependability – target for them is mostly safety, whereas dependability also involve availability and reliability.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="on-doing-things-better" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-doing-things-better">On doing things better</h2>
<ul>
<li>2025-03-Reading-Papers-Efficiently</li>
<li>Doing-Literature-Review</li>
<li>Systematic-Literature-Review</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="on-beginning-the-phd-with-a-survey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-beginning-the-phd-with-a-survey">On beginning the PhD with a survey</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>It doesn’t matter if I end up doing a SLR or not; I have to start reading systematically. That means, finding the gist of the paper and seeing the context, the assumptions, the pros and cons. See the paper in the big picture.</li>
<li>I should start cataloguing what I’m reading.</li>
<li>Create a new note with a set of questions that <em>must</em> be answered for every paper being analyzed in the context of my research.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="dependability-issue-global-and-project-specific-notes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dependability-issue-global-and-project-specific-notes">Dependability issue: global and project-specific notes</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>It’s often the case for a given reference – a paper for instance – I analyze it in its own note in my main vault but need to refine or enrich it with additional information.</li>
<li>This additional information is often <em>project-specific</em> and undesirable in a more generic context – which is the case of my main vault.</li>
<li>How can I add new notes to a project that reference the global note? So I don’t repeat myself and still maintain consistency during an analysis?</li>
<li>I think the concept of parent note might be handy. This parent note can be linked in the metadata of the child note as: <code>parent: example-parent-note</code> – here assuming a wikilink format.</li>
<li>Just for the context I plan to apply this for the following workflow:
<ol type="1">
<li>I create a new global note for a reference – let us assume a conference paper. There we add all relevant metadata of the publication <em>and</em> my general remarks and notes about it (often answers for what/why/how/weaknesses/future work)</li>
<li>In a separated vault/repository – where I am performing a literature review – I create a new note which references the global note through the <em>parent</em> property, as described in 4.</li>
<li>In this new note I add the survey-relevant (or more abstractly, project-specific) information.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="thoughts-on-executing-a-slr" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thoughts-on-executing-a-slr">Thoughts on executing a SLR</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Instead of blindly digesting all papers, one by one, I could apply a smarter approach:</li>
<li>Sort by last author – this is normally the head researcher. That way I sort by the research group. Then apply a sort by first author. Digest together all papers of the research group grouped by first author.</li>
<li>This makes understanding the evolution of the thought-process inside a research grouper easier. Furthermore, it’s easier for me to digest and process ideas that are correlated and/or are built on top of the previously defined concepts.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="concepts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="concepts">Concepts</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hazard, Risk, Safety-Engineering, Functional-Safety</li>
<li>Safety-Engineering vs Security</li>
<li>HARA, Risk-Assessment</li>
<li>Dynamic-Risk-Assessment == Risk-Assessment-at-Runtime ? find out</li>
<li>DRM vs Dynamic-Risk-Assessment</li>
<li>Machine-Learning-Models, Data-driven-Model</li>
<li>SIL, ASIL</li>
<li>DDI, ConSert, U-map</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="standards" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="standards">Standards</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>IEC-61508: More abstract functional safety for EE</li>
<li>ISO-26262: Functional safety for Road Vehicles</li>
<li>IEC-31010: Risk assessment techniques</li>
<li>DIN-SPEC-92005: Uncertainty quantification in ML</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>phd</category>
  <category>research-dump</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/2025-03-Research-Dump.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pin your habits</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Pin-your-habits.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The concept of taking note whenever you are about to do a good or a bad habit.</p>
<p>Mindfully observing your feelings, sensorial inputs and circumstances that triggered this behaviour provides information and reduces influences of automatized and heavily-ingrained neural pathways in place.</p>
<p>Ask yourself:</p>
<ul>
<li>What led me to wanting to do this bad habit?</li>
<li>How am I feeling right now? Bored? Agitated? Anxious?</li>
<li>Where am I?</li>
<li>What I did just before wanting to do this bad habit?</li>
</ul>
<p>Logging these instances provide a way to recognize patterns that often lead to the bad behaviour.</p>
<p>When the pattern is there, the target is clear. One way to mitigate is to apply the concept of TAPs</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Pin-your-habits.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On the fragility of claims</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/On-the-fragility-of-claims.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>AG1, Andrew Huberman, more of the same?</p>
<p>After watching following video <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=wb1g-Cbcjwo">YouTube</a> I couldn’t stop thinking how easily we can get lied to. It’s not that I’m arguing they are blatantly lying about AG1 efficacy. It’s that we can get lured by claims so easily.. just because they are wrapped in a neat packaging and overly sprinkled by trendy qualifiers we stop doubting the claims that are made.</p>
<p>Are they even meaningful claims? Are they even worth anything? Or are they just more of the same, a candy bar.</p>
<p>It’s not that people that I think are knowledgeable lie. It’s that every claim is fragile without the necessary critical thinking backing it up. It must happen in my mind - and only there, an unavoidable step to achieve truth; science.</p>
<p>How easily can we fall victim from people, who <em>maybe</em> not even want to do that. It’s not <em>only</em> their fault; it’s from the lazy actuation of my critical senses.</p>
<p>Is it fair to demand this capability from everyone? A good question. Probably not.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/On-the-fragility-of-claims.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Work Session</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Work-Session.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A Work Session is a time-bound, goal-oriented method for getting work done. Breaking it down:</p>
<ul>
<li>It has a fixed start time and duration.</li>
<li>It includes a list of well-defined SMART goals, ensuring that results and deliverables are clearly measurable.</li>
</ul>
<p>The method incorporates principles from Pomodoro and Deep Work, creating a structured work slot where:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Deep work is encouraged.</li>
<li>Rest is prioritized.</li>
<li>Distractions are minimized.</li>
<li>Purpose is at the forefront.</li>
</ol>
<section id="the-work-session-ws" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-work-session-ws">The Work Session (WS)</h2>
<p>The core unit of this method is the Work Session (WS). A WS consists of two halves, each lasting between 40 to 60 minutes. It’s <em>recommended</em>, but not mandatory, to take a short 5–10 minute break between the halves.</p>
<p>This break is yours to use as you see fit—if you’ve been working at a screen, consider standing up and stretching. There are no strict rules on how to spend this time.</p>
<p>However, after completing both halves, you’ve successfully finished a WS. Congratulations! You now deserve a longer break of 20–50 minutes. Use this time to recharge—go for a jog, train, or do something that improves your well-being. Embrace Serendipity and have a conversation with someone. Taking this break seriously is just as important as the work itself.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-three-steps-of-a-ws" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-three-steps-of-a-ws">The Three Steps of a WS</h2>
<p>There are three key steps to starting a structured WS.</p>
<section id="plan" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plan">1. Plan</h3>
<p>Define what you want to accomplish. Use smartly structured tasks and choose one actionable step to focus on.</p>
<p>Create a new file in your favorite text editor (or an analog notebook) and clearly write down the task you intend to complete during this WS.</p>
<p>If the task is large, break it into smaller, manageable chunks—Divide-and-Conquer!</p>
<p><strong>Most importantly, ensure that each task has a crystal-clear endpoint.</strong></p>
</section>
<section id="work" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="work">2. Work</h3>
<p>This is the step you’re familiar with, but with one important addition: <strong>logging</strong>.</p>
<p>In the same file where you wrote your task, document what you’re working on, any obstacles you encounter, insights you gain, and any other relevant details. Keep the bar low—if something seems even mildly relevant, jot it down. You’ll thank yourself later.</p>
<p>Logging your work:</p>
<ul>
<li>Creates a record of your progress.</li>
<li>Reinforces the value of your efforts.</li>
<li>Enhances traceability, helping you track the challenges you faced and the solutions you applied.</li>
</ul>
<p>Consider these scenarios:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Boss:</strong> “What did you accomplish last month?” <strong>You:</strong> <em>A few clicks away from the answer.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>You, six months later:</strong> “What was I doing in this hobby project again?” <em>A few clicks away from the answer.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>You, after reading your notes:</strong> “Oh! I got stuck here last time. Now I know exactly where to pick up and move forward!”</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="long-pause" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="long-pause">3. Long Pause</h3>
<p>Once the WS is over, you deserve a long break. Be kind to yourself—if you need a few extra minutes, take them. However, before ending your WS, ensure that your task is either:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Completed</strong>, or</li>
<li><strong>Replanned</strong> for a future session.</li>
</ol>
<p>Since you’re actively logging, you’ll have a clear sense of whether your current WS is enough to complete the task. If not, take a few minutes to revise and break it down further. This is completely normal—over time, you’ll develop a better sense of what can realistically be achieved in a WS.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="example" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example">Example</h2>
<ul>
<li>In 1.5 hours, I will:</li>
<li>Implement the DAO component of the app.</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>org</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Work-Session.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Case for an App Like Readwise</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/The-case-for-an-app-like-Readwise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The problem Readwise aims to solve is one I find frustrating: highlighting content and never revisiting it. Their approach—sending email digests of highlights—should work for me, assuming I check my inbox regularly. Yet, I’m still not a subscriber, and the reason boils down to a gut feeling.</p>
<p>That same instinct is what led me to write in plain text and store my information using simple, transparent methods rather than relying on an external app that may not be around in a few years.</p>
<p>Dependency on another tool introduces complexity and friction. The equation is straightforward: if the value a tool provides outweighs the added complexity, it’s worth using. The challenge lies in measuring both value and complexity. But in cases like this, the brain often finds a quick answer—manifesting as intuition. And so far, my intuition has served me well.</p>
<p>At the same time, I have too many data silos in my life, and I want to break down the walls between them.</p>
<section id="why-do-i-want-to-remember-my-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-do-i-want-to-remember-my-highlights">Why Do I Want to Remember My Highlights?</h2>
<p>What is a highlight, really?</p>
<p>The meaning of a highlight depends on perspective. For me, it’s a <em>wow</em> moment—something that struck me as unique, whether because of its aesthetic, phrasing, or a fresh take on an idea.</p>
<p>If I saw my highlights every day, I’d remember books and articles better. It would give me a second chance to engage with ideas, to refine and reinforce them. I <em>want</em> that. It’s a clear pain point for me.</p>
<p>The ideal solution would be an interface so seamlessly integrated with my mind that it captures highlights from any medium I consume—whether digital or physical.</p>
</section>
<section id="my-current-system" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-current-system">My Current System</h2>
<p>I highlight text in Kindle, Zotero, Google Keep, my PC, my tablet, and my phone—not to mention physical books and documents. Each of these platforms has its own format, and none of them talk to each other.</p>
<p>At the moment, my notes remain isolated. I occasionally review and organize my Google Keep notes, archiving old ones and consolidating key points. I no longer bookmark pages in my browser—I just save links there.</p>
<p>I also like Kindle’s sync between my phone and tablet, and I wouldn’t want to give that up.</p>
</section>
<section id="rethinking-the-problem" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rethinking-the-problem">Rethinking the Problem</h2>
<p>There are countless ways I consume information, and some (like physical books) don’t allow for easy API integration. External tools would be needed.</p>
<p>But maybe a <em>highlight</em> isn’t the most important thing. A raw highlight is just a snippet—it lacks context. What’s far more valuable is a <strong>summary of the key ideas</strong>, enriched with my own insights.</p>
<p>This is what’s worth preserving. And this can be done <em>independently of any specific media format</em>. It simply requires an intentional process after consuming information—digesting, compiling, and simplifying key takeaways.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-actual-solution" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-actual-solution">The Actual Solution</h2>
<p>The real solution isn’t software—it’s <strong>a habit</strong>: taking time to reflect on and consolidate what I’ve learned. If I use a simple system (like text files and Git) for this step, I’m not locked into any particular platform. I can do it from my phone, tablet, or computer—anywhere I have access to my notes.</p>
<p>In other words, instead of trying to integrate every new format and tool into my workflow, the simplest approach is to <strong>shift the focus from isolated highlights to structured reflections</strong>—blended with my personal experiences and evolving understanding.</p>
<p>This approach, however, doesn’t address the challenge of recall. That’s where Readwise excels: by sending daily digests that resurface past insights.</p>
<p>So, if there’s one tool I <em>would</em> subscribe to, it would be one that generates digests from <strong>my</strong> markdown notes—aggregating them into a gentle, well-timed invitation to review and reflect.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/The-case-for-an-app-like-Readwise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Guitar Setup</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Guitar-Setup.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Setting up a guitar involves the following steps:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Find the right string set for your tuning</li>
<li>Adjust Neck Relief (truss rod)</li>
<li>Adjust Action</li>
<li>Adjust Nut Height</li>
<li>Adjust Entonation</li>
</ol>
<section id="knowing-the-system" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="knowing-the-system">Knowing the System</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/gtantm01.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>gtantm01</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="buy-the-correct-string-set-for-your-desired-tuning-and-guitar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="buy-the-correct-string-set-for-your-desired-tuning-and-guitar">Buy the correct string set for your desired tuning and guitar</h2>
<p>I really like the calculator from <a href="https://tension.stringjoy.com/">StringJoy</a>, see Calculating-Guitar-Tension</p>
<p>There you can input the important parameters: the desired tuning and the scale length (also supports individual scale lengths - useful for multiscale guitars).</p>
<p>I have no idea from where, but I heard the tension should land between [18, 25] lbs. Currently, I’m around 19 lbs on the lowest string of my 7 strings and it’s quite good for my taste.</p>
<p>Try searching for available guitar sets and changing the gauges in the calculator to them from the sets, in order to achieve a value in that range.</p>
</section>
<section id="adjust-neck-relief" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-neck-relief">Adjust Neck Relief</h2>
<p>This site is way better than my half-assed explanation below: https://www.taylorguitars.com/support/maintenance/truss-rod-adjustments</p>
<p>Neck relief is how much space is left in the playing position between the strings and the frets.</p>
<p>I personally measure in playing position and with all strings in the desired tuning; that way I guarantee the same tension is being applied in the neck during measurement and playing.</p>
<p>I don’t use any specialized tool to do that, only a business card and a capo.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Play all strings on all frets; where do you encounter fret buzz? Refer to the picture below to find the problem.</li>
<li>First assess the current state: put capo in the 1st fret and a finger in any fret where the neck is already in contact with the guitar frame. You want to use the string as a reference straight line and ignore other parameters as nut height and action.</li>
<li>Slide a business card between fret and lowest string around the 7th fret</li>
<li>You want the thickness of the card to be the distance between fret and string; so if it slides too loosely, then you may have backwards bow; conversely, if it is too tight, forward bow. Compare with the pic, does the problem matches the measurement? (idk about 7+ strings guitars, I tried to do this procedure measuring with the 6th string, ignoring the 7th, and it worked nicely)</li>
<li>Now find the trust rod adjustment nut. In my guitar it was in the headstock, covered by a piece of plastic. Pick the correct allen key and do adjustments in 1/8th of a turn, as the pic suggests.</li>
<li>Remember to always retune the guitar for the correct tension to be there. The tension impacts relief, so you need it to be there, in order for the measurement to make any sense.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/maxresdefault.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>maxresdefault</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>2024-05-04 Currently moving clockwise (reference plane with normal headstock -&gt; bridge) (suspecting forward bow)</p>
</section>
<section id="adjust-action" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-action">Adjust Action</h2>
<p>Action is another important adjustment to make. It’s the space between string and fret. Everybody measures on the 12th, I suggest you do it there too. It enables to eventually compare the value to some standard value or to some random guy in a forum that swears by 1mm without fret buzz on the lowest string.</p>
<p>You can use a ruler, filler gauges or a caliper to do the measurements. Personally, I don’t measure it at all. Let me tell you why.</p>
<p>Find these guys in your bridge:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/Unbenannt.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Unbenannt</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are two of them for each string. It suppose it should follow the curvature of the neck. So whenever you are adjusting them, try to do your best to adjust the same amount on both of them. This is easy to do. Just put the key and make a mental note where it is, adjust in quarter/half or full turns and just replicate on the other nut.</p>
<p>I tend to leave them the lowest possible, before I start hearing any fret buzz. For the lowest strings I leave them a bit higher, so they can have more sustain.</p>
</section>
<section id="adjust-nut-height" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-nut-height">Adjust Nut Height</h2>
<p>Never done that. Heard you have to file the nut slots with special files or just sliding an old string back and forth.</p>
<p>If everything you done so far didn’t lead to good results, chances are that nut height is your problem.</p>
<p>I would personally take the guitar for a professional setup; otherwise I would risk making it unplayable for the day or week, maybe having to order another nut.</p>
</section>
<section id="adjust-entonation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjust-entonation">Adjust Entonation</h2>
<p>This should be the last thing you do, after everything is properly set up. Follow the picture below to adjust the entonation, aka. why my higher frets are so out of tune.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/assets/Adjust-string-length.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Adjust-string-length</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="final-words" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-words">Final words</h2>
<p>This is about it. This knowledge I gathered from the web.</p>
<p>The pics are between the first ones that show when you google action/relief, they seem to be used in many sites without citation making it impossible to find the OG source. If you happen to know the author, just write me up and I add it right away.</p>
<p>Oh, I applied in a bass. It also works.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>guide</category>
  <category>music/guitar</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Guitar-Setup.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Preserving what I consume</title>
  <link>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Preserving-what-I-consume.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Read. Watch. Sense. Take control of what I consume and steer it toward creative output—not obsessively, but in a way that passively expands my worldview.</p>
<p>I wonder how I can do this better. Is a directory full of text the best way to cultivate new ideas, or just another way to let them fade away?</p>
<p>I seek a modern approach, though I still value the old ways—they led me here, after all.</p>
<p>The question itself is somewhat misframed. Preserving what I consume is never the goal—nor should it be. Wisdom and intelligence don’t come from mere accumulation. Knowledge, maybe. But meaningful progress comes from applying, adapting, and transforming what I’ve learned—regardless of whether the outcome is right or wrong.</p>
<p>How can I foster a productive chain of thought that leads to a more rewarding perspective on the world? Not a hedonistic one, but one that is deeply, humanly fulfilling.</p>
<p>Writing brings me closer to that. So does publishing my ideas. But hoarding? That only creates the illusion of work. The illusion of productivity. And sometimes, even being productive hides in the same shadow.</p>
<p>Bear with me—I’m just beginning to learn.</p>
<p>I see value in this writing. I also see value in the same thing I dismissed two hours ago. Funny how that works. Every day, things shift—priorities, goals, tools—changing shape and significance. Understanding that brings me closer to myself. Frustration is inevitable; stoicism is my first reflex. Beyond that lies uncharted territory, unique to each of us.</p>
<p>Learning is repetition—but repetition shouldn’t be forced. You didn’t learn your mother tongue with Anki. The key is to create an environment where repetition happens naturally, where failure isn’t a setback but part of the process. Remove external barriers that prevent this from happening.</p>
<p>Technical skills are just one type of useful skill. Sometimes, the mind craves something else.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>essay</category>
  <guid>https://blog.mmolina.me/posts/Preserving-what-I-consume.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
